<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Journal</title>
<link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/self/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/self/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.450</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Dec 2023 14:41:16 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Multiple Games</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/self/2023-12-14 multiple games.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>My work requires a lot of concentration. I was good at school because I could focus my mind on specific tasks and immerse myself in them. This ability is, of course, a great skill to have today, with human progress relying on our capacity to concentrate like this.</p>
<p>However, life doesn’t operate in the same way. You’re playing multiple games at the same time - work, relationships, health, money, career - and you need to be able to switch back and forth between them as necessary. Each of these games has its own rules and requires different skill sets. Still, being able to focus on one game at a time is essential for success in them.</p>
<p>A meta-skill you need to develop in life is the ability to 1) quickly switch tasks, and 2) once switched, devote yourself wholeheartedly to them. This includes adjusting your emotional state. You might be completely stressed at work, but as soon as you switch to playing the relationships game, you need to load the relevant state into your working memory and stash the work-related state away for later recall.</p>
<p>This is both a good and a bad thing. The bad part is, of course, that you need to acquire this new meta-skill of fast context switching and come up with some organizational principle to manage the data from multiple games. The good parts are more subtle. Often, the negative emotions don’t survive the recall. Unless you’re having a streak of bad luck, you might be doing well in at least one game. Whenever things get too overwhelming in another game, you can switch to this one, even if only momentarily.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>self</category>
  <category>mindfulness</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/self/2023-12-14 multiple games.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Dec 2023 14:41:16 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Life is Hard</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/self/2023-12-13 life is hard.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I was under some stress and anxiety, which, looking back, was completely unnecessary and self-imposed, but did not feel so in the midst of it. Then, suddenly, yesterday, it thawed and gradually went away. I’m trying to figure out what helped me alleviate it.</p>
<p>The simplest reason was perhaps that I had a lot of free time with no deadlines, so I could spend more time contemplating, meditating, and self-observing, thereby appreciating the absurdity of it. This is, of course, the closest we can get to a panacea - the solution to all your problems is to look at yourself inwardly, and given enough time and attention, things would resolve. But I do not always have the luxury to take such long breaks. Perhaps this means that I’m doomed, and when life gets busy, I will get stressed and anxious. All I can do is take small breaks and try to maintain a functional state of anxiety. Which brings me to my second point.</p>
<p>You don’t have to eliminate stress and anxiety. What really sent the ball rolling down the hill for me was a deep realization and acceptance of the fact that life is just hard. There is no reason for it to be otherwise. Sometimes, when something goes in your favor, you start subconsciously hoping for a “happily ever after.” But such a state is purely mythical.</p>
<p>Another realization I had was that, while it is true that things are not all well for me, I just know that sometime, at an unknown time, at an unknown place, things are going to get much worse. I will have some unbearable emotional or physical pain, and if I expect to find equanimity then, I better find equanimity now when things are mostly good with a few wrinkles.</p>
<p>Life is hard, but that’s ok.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>self</category>
  <category>mindfulness</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/self/2023-12-13 life is hard.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Dec 2023 17:24:39 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Life As A Video Game</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/self/2023-12-13 life as a game.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Even though meditation practice is about experience and going beyond words and concepts, the right framing using the right concepts helps to get you there. I was listening to a podcast yesterday on a long drive and wasn’t feeling so great, and the podcast was about the elusive state of Flow. Just as I heard it, I tried to get into a state of flow and immediately my brain turned the road into a video game. I was back inside a <em>Fast and Furious</em> game, but I was neither fast nor furious. Suddenly everything changed. I just imagined the cars in front of me as obstacles I needed to avoid to clear the level. I set my own objectives: the least number of brakes and lane changes. I managed to get myself into a state of flow on I-95!</p>
<p>I hope I am able to replicate this in other scenarios. I have played video games for so long that I would rather live in them than in the real world, and what I’m realizing is that I can trick my brain into forgetting the distinction between the two worlds!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>self</category>
  <category>mindfulness</category>
  <category>framing</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/self/2023-12-13 life as a game.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Dec 2023 13:11:30 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>You Know Enough</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/self/2023-12-12 you know enough.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I’ve been feeling a bit irritated, scattered, and frustrated lately. Recent chaos in my life has triggered this state of mind.</p>
<p>I’ve noticed that I keep listening to meditation podcasts and Dharma talks, subconsciously hoping that they’ll help my mind settle down. However, I’m reminded of a point Sam Harris makes in one of his conversations (I’m paraphrasing): there’s only so much conceptual knowledge you need to acquire from others. Sure, you can continue listening to these full-time meditators and gain new insights, but that won’t significantly impact your life. You need to accept that <strong>you know enough</strong>. Now it’s time to buckle down and take extreme ownership.</p>
<p>For me, this means recognizing that my state of frustration and irritation won’t dissipate if I bombard myself with Buddhist wisdom. I need to accept that I am responsible for this state. Although my circumstances triggered it, I am the one sustaining and aggravating it by being myopic and undisciplined.</p>
<p>I know what I need to do. I need to stop searching for more knowledge from others and accept my state for what it is, working on it in ways <strong>I already know</strong>. The promise of meditation is not happiness, but liberation. With a sufficient understanding of self, hopefully, this state will pass sooner rather than later.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>self</category>
  <category>meditation</category>
  <category>practice</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/self/2023-12-12 you know enough.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2023 18:59:56 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Pre-Planning</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/self/2023-12-06 preplanning.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>There are two habits I am very serious about developing:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Regulating my sleep – going to bed early and waking up early.</li>
<li>Planning ahead of time.</li>
</ol>
<p>I know people who prepare their entire courses during breaks and then just teach during the semester. They have their lectures, homework, quizzes, and even announcements and emails preprogrammed and just focus on execution during the semester. Pedagogically, I do not favor this approach as I teach better when I improvise during the semester and adapt to my students’ needs.</p>
<p>However, I can no longer sustain improvisation. This semester, I’m teaching just one course on a trivial subject to a small group of students, yet I am overwhelmed by the number of weekly deadlines. Soon, I will be teaching more challenging courses to a larger student body and will have numerous administrative tasks, possibly with additional research duties.</p>
<p>This means preplanning is no longer a luxury, but a <strong>necessity</strong>.</p>
<p>This issue also affected me during my camping trip. I knew months in advance that I would be camping at Joshua Tree National Park. I could have packed and prepared days, if not weeks, in advance. Instead, I packed at the last minute, resulting in a miserable, anxiety-filled, and sleep-deprived trip to the airport.</p>
<p>Now I know the <em>what</em>. I need to figure out the <em>how</em>.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>self</category>
  <category>shortcomings</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/self/2023-12-06 preplanning.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 06 Dec 2023 19:05:50 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Exam Disruptions</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/self/2023-12-06 exam disruption.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>In my most productive days, I consistently track my time using Toggl. I switch the timer as I switch activities, ensuring my entire day is logged. However, this system isn’t completely stable for me and tends to fail when disruptions occur in my life.</p>
<p>Lately, I haven’t been keeping track of my time, and I can pinpoint the last significant disruption to the second exam of my course! I’ve always known that exams are a major stressor for me, but I didn’t realize the impact was so pronounced.</p>
<p>This realization of course does not remove the stressor but now I know what to look out for after the exam.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>self</category>
  <category>life-events</category>
  <category>caution</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/self/2023-12-06 exam disruption.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 06 Dec 2023 18:57:06 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
