<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Journal</title>
<link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/uncategorized/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/uncategorized/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.450</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2023 00:59:31 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Casey Neistat</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/uncategorized/2023-10-30 casey neistat.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I try to stay away from the internet meme culture as much as possible. I no longer find it funny to make fun of people unintentionally (I do still love absurd humor and find many of the controversial comics funny).</p>
<p>I saw a Casey Neistat thumbnail on Nerdwriter1’s channel but I stayed away from it thinking that he’s just another internet meme personality.</p>
<p>But for some reason, I watched one video of Neistat and got hooked. I immediately realized that this wasn’t another internet troll but a master at his craft.</p>
<p>I love that when I open his videos, most of the time I do not know what’s going to happen. And yet, I’m somehow convinced that the video is going to go well! Behind his “bro” facade he is a master storyteller. Rather, his “bro” facade is part of his storytelling act.</p>
<p>I also love his cinematography, editing, music mixing, just everything. Never a boring video.</p>
<p>I’m writing all this because I learned about his work ethic and feel very inspired by it. For quite some time now, I have been struggling with my sleep and work routine. I’m slowly improving but as I’m writing this I’m realizing that I lack role models in this area. The people in my life either don’t do work they like or work hard obsessively for the sake or working hard. But now I have Neistat! He is someone whose work and skill I admire and understand and whose work ethic I hope to emulate.</p>
<p>I hope that this is the kick I needed to pull myself up by the bootstraps. Of course, I feel very motivated and inspired <em>now</em> but the real test is whether this is going to last. Only time will tell.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/C-Cvl3_CH2A?si=RW4KEK-zT6Y3olaE" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>



 ]]></description>
  <category>habits</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/uncategorized/2023-10-30 casey neistat.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2023 00:59:31 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Board Games in Baltimore</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/uncategorized/2023-09-04 boardgames.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I have been trying out some board games groups around Baltimore. Sadly I could not find any in the city itself but I found quite a few in the surrounding areas. I have been to two events of far and already learned quite a few new games.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/339/quiddler">Quiddler</a></li>
<li><a href="https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/131357/coup">Coup</a></li>
<li><a href="https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/262543/wavelength">Wavelength</a></li>
<li><a href="https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/158268/karma">Karma</a></li>
<li><a href="https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/258/fluxx">Fluxx</a></li>
<li><a href="https://boardgamegeek.com/boardgame/164840/monopoly-deal">Monopoly Deal</a></li>
</ul>
<p>They were all quick games and fun to play. If I were to buy any of these then it would be Wavelength. All the others were card games and fun to play with people who have never played board games before.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>boardgames</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/uncategorized/2023-09-04 boardgames.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 04 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Group Exercise</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/uncategorized/2023-08-30 group exercise.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I like to think that I am generally a very fit person. I exercise almost everyday and generally lead an active life. Just for fun, I recently tried a Yoga Sculpt class and it kicked my ass.</p>
<p>This made me realize two things:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>When working out alone, it’s easy to not be fully honest with oneself. I probably take longer breaks, get sidetracked by my phone, or choose lighter weights when I could handle heavier ones.</li>
<li>We can often push ourselves more than we think. I never knew an hour-long HIIT session with weights, like Yoga Sculpt, was something I could do. I’m surprised I hadn’t tried it earlier.</li>
</ol>
<p>I once tried a yoga class via livestream, but it didn’t feel the same. The poses might have been identical, but the intensity was different.</p>
<p>I’ve started to see the benefits of group classes. They push you harder and offer new experiences you might not encounter otherwise.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>journal</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/uncategorized/2023-08-30 group exercise.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 30 Aug 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Chandrayaan-3</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/uncategorized/2023-08-23 chandrayaan 3.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>India landed Chandrayaan-3 on the Moon! Amazing!!!</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/gvj3w59EaFM" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>
<p><img src="https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/uncategorized/https:/media.tenor.com/XUAONVsG6qIAAAAC/leonardo-dicaprio-clapping.gif" class="img-fluid"></p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>journal</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/uncategorized/2023-08-23 chandrayaan 3.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2023 18:45:49 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Starting Your Day Right</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/uncategorized/2023-08-23 starting your day right.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>There is a strong correlation between my daily habits and my level of productivity. When I’m at my peak performance, everything feels automated and flowing.</p>
<p>In the past month, I relocated to Baltimore. Prior to that, I was frequently on the move, both for work and family commitments. As a result of which, my routine has been completely upended, and my habits are in complete disarray.</p>
<p>I came across this <a href="https://dailystoic.com/marcus-aurelius-daily-habits/">post on Stoicism</a> (something I greatly admire) which, among other things, talks about starting your day right. This made me realize how I’ve been swept up by the unproductive habit of checking my phone first thing in the morning.</p>
<p>Fortunately, I’ve just finished assembling my writing desk by a lovely corner window. My coffee is brewing and my trusty iPad is charged. Time to get back to morning journaling again. Hopefully, even when life gets busy and chaotic, I’ll have the stamina and discipline to keep up with this incredibly useful habit.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/images/writingDesk.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">My writing desk</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>stoicism</category>
  <category>habits</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/uncategorized/2023-08-23 starting your day right.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2023 14:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
