<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Journal</title>
<link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.450</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Dec 2023 15:39:27 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Setting Intention</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-12-07 setting intention.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>One of the best “hacks” for being mindful and present is to set intentions before starting any task. This includes tasks like planning and concentrated thinking. You just “let your brain know” that this is what it needs to be doing now and it can return to other tasks afterward.</p>
<p>This aligns with the analogy that the brain is a blind automaton with different parts working in parallel. There is communication between the various parts, but this communication is often delayed and imperfect. By setting intentions, you are sending a strong message from one part of the brain to another.</p>
<p>Like right now, there is a lot of chaos happening around me. My internet is down, and I’m supposed to be in a meeting. I have a bunch of deadlines today and I need to get back to planning several things soon. If I just let my mind wander, it will keep jumping from one task to another without actually resolving anything, just increasing my anxiety. Instead, I have decided, as much as possible, that this is my writing time. I do still get thoughts about other things and keep a notebook with me to jot them down to return to them after I’m done. But having this clear intention of writing is essential for me to make it to the end of this sentence with full commitment.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>meditation</category>
  <category>mindfulness</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-12-07 setting intention.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 07 Dec 2023 15:39:27 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Being Present</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-30 present moment.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>“Be Here Now,” the classic book by Ram Dass, is supposed to encapsulate the project of meditation. The more I struggle with meditation, the more I realize how central this principle is to the practice.</p>
<p>My brain is constantly future-looking, sometimes in small ways - I might be brewing coffee and simultaneously thinking about the joy of drinking it afterwards, or I might be biking to work while thinking of what I’m going to do in class today - and sometimes in large ways - I might be doing something mundane like laundry while worrying about my career and long-term future. We are genetically, culturally, and habitually in this constant state of chasing the future.</p>
<p>Why is this bad? Because it represents habituation and a lack of intention. One of the goals of mindfulness is the recognition of conditioning and intentionally choosing to either do something or not. Of course, future planning is a good thing, but it does not need to be done constantly. You need to decide to plan for the future, take care of it, and then let go and return to the present.</p>
<p>It is, of course, easier said than done. I am not sure if it is even possible to be fully present in the current moment. But mindfulness teachings come to the rescue again - the goal is never the reason to do something; the process is. You need to enjoy this process of recognizing that the mind is future-looking and decide if this is where you want it to be. Whether you want it or not, you just make a decision and let go.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>mindfulness</category>
  <category>meditation</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-30 present moment.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 07 Dec 2023 15:00:47 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Saying No</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-27 saying no.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>In a podcast episode on waking up, Oliver Burkeman talks about the necessity to say no to certain things in life because you only have a finite amount of time. This becomes clear when you do the calculation involving the time available and the time required to get things done. This is further emphasized by the fact that we don’t always have the will, energy, or capacity to do the things we would like to do.</p>
<p>Two things worth pointing out:</p>
<ul>
<li>You have to learn to say no to things that you <em>want to do</em>. Just yesterday, I was at a yoga class which was overcrowded. I usually love staying for the final resting pose but I knew that if I stayed until the end, it would take me forever to leave. So, reluctantly, I left early. I still got most of the benefits of the class and managed to leave on time by making a small sacrifice.</li>
<li>There is a difference between conceptually understanding something and experientially understanding it. The effect a concept has on your life is much greater once you’ve internalized it. Even though it’s <em>obvious</em> that you have to say no to things, we don’t always do it. And even when we do, we tend to feel guilty or irritated about it. One has to realize that there is just no alternative. This is a consequence of our finiteness that we need to accept and move on.</li>
</ul>



 ]]></description>
  <category>podcast</category>
  <category>oliver burkeman</category>
  <category>waking up</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-27 saying no.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 27 Nov 2023 12:59:36 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Beginner’s Mind</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-23 beginners mind.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I was listening to a <a href="https://radiolab.org/podcast/interstitium">Radiolab podcast</a> that concluded with a quote by Suzuki Roshi: <em>“In the beginner’s mind there are many possibilities, but in the expert’s there are few.”</em></p>
<p>I’ve never given this much thought, as I’m not particularly drawn to the Zen traditions of koans and contradictions. However, hearing this quote at the end of a science podcast really caught me off-guard and made me see it from a different perspective. I can’t pinpoint exactly what this feeling is, but I feel a tingling sensation hinting at something deeper.</p>
<p>What is it that I’m not seeing? Is it related to my life? My work? Teaching? Meditation?</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>buddhism</category>
  <category>zen</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-23 beginners mind.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2023 19:58:51 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>You Fall to Your Systems</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-23 systems.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>James Clear, the author of “Atomic Habits,” has a quote: “You do not rise to the level of your goals. You fall to the level of your systems.”</p>
<p>I experienced this just today. I completed a five-day hiking trip through the Mojave Desert in Joshua Tree National Park. It was difficult, tiring, exhilarating, and rewarding - everything you’d expect. On the long walks, I brainstormed ways to improve my life, made many plans for the future, and ended up feeling very optimistic.</p>
<p>However, when the trip ended, I just crashed. Surprisingly, I was not mentally or physically exhausted and needed no time to recover. But I had lost my “systems.” During the hikes, I woke up, had breakfast, drove to the trailheads, hiked, returned to the campsite, had dinner, and went to bed. This routine was my daily pattern. Suddenly, I needed to <em>decide</em> what to do next, and I couldn’t do it effectively. I ended up wasting an entire day watching meaningless videos.</p>
<p>“You do not rise to the level of your goals. You fall to the level of your systems.”</p>
<p>To maintain the mental state I achieved during the trip and act on any of the ideas I had, the first thing I need to do is develop good “systems,” i.e., habits and routines. These need to be simple and maintainable.</p>
<p>My first goal, which is more of a habit, is to <strong>wake up every day at 6 a.m.</strong>, no matter what. If I go to bed late, too bad for me. I will also try to avoid drinking coffee, taking naps during the day, and consuming alcohol. The latter are not difficult as long as I can stick to the first one.</p>
<p>If possible, I’d also like to go for a run, walk, or bike ride as soon as I wake up. When I was hiking, one thing I loved was waking up to the fresh, cold morning air. I suspect it set an uplifting tone for the rest of the day.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>habits</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-23 systems.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2023 15:51:10 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Love the Process</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-01 process vs goal.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>There are two ways of approaching any task and life in general:</p>
<ul>
<li>goal oriented</li>
<li>process oriented</li>
</ul>
<p>For some reason, very likely a mix of cultural and biological, the default is the first approach. You do things in order to get somewhere, to accomplish something.</p>
<p>One of the most important teachings of the various contemplative traditions like Buddhism, Stoicism is that in order to find any semblance of equanimity you need to take the process oriented approach - love the process. The goal is often unattainable and impractical and even when it is attained the attainment itself is momentary and fleeting and once you’re done with it you’re left with a hollowness and a lack of direction.</p>
<p>If you want to run regularly, then you cannot make your running contingent on the next marathon. Every marathon will be over sooner than you’d like. And there will inevitably be long stretches of time in your life when you won’t be able to participate in any running events. If you truly want to become a runner then you should enjoy the process of running for its own sake. You should participate in running events because you’re a runner and not the other way around.</p>
<p>The book “Atomic Habits” has a very good way of putting this - instead of saying that you want to run, you phrase it as you want to become a runner. Instead of saying that you want to read x number of books each year, you say that you want to become an avid reader. This moves the focus from the goal to the process itself.</p>
<p>You can extend this to the broader extent of life. You cannot decide to work hard because you want to accomplish certain goals. Rather you’re able to accomplish your goals in life because you’re a hard working person. The arrow of causality points in the other direction.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>mindfulness</category>
  <category>philosophy</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-01 process vs goal.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2023 17:38:38 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
