<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Journal</title>
<link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.450</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2023 19:58:51 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Beginner’s Mind</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-23 beginners mind.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I was listening to a <a href="https://radiolab.org/podcast/interstitium">Radiolab podcast</a> that concluded with a quote by Suzuki Roshi: <em>“In the beginner’s mind there are many possibilities, but in the expert’s there are few.”</em></p>
<p>I’ve never given this much thought, as I’m not particularly drawn to the Zen traditions of koans and contradictions. However, hearing this quote at the end of a science podcast really caught me off-guard and made me see it from a different perspective. I can’t pinpoint exactly what this feeling is, but I feel a tingling sensation hinting at something deeper.</p>
<p>What is it that I’m not seeing? Is it related to my life? My work? Teaching? Meditation?</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>buddhism</category>
  <category>zen</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-23 beginners mind.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2023 19:58:51 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>You Fall to Your Systems</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-23 systems.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>James Clear, the author of “Atomic Habits,” has a quote: “You do not rise to the level of your goals. You fall to the level of your systems.”</p>
<p>I experienced this just today. I completed a five-day hiking trip through the Mojave Desert in Joshua Tree National Park. It was difficult, tiring, exhilarating, and rewarding - everything you’d expect. On the long walks, I brainstormed ways to improve my life, made many plans for the future, and ended up feeling very optimistic.</p>
<p>However, when the trip ended, I just crashed. Surprisingly, I was not mentally or physically exhausted and needed no time to recover. But I had lost my “systems.” During the hikes, I woke up, had breakfast, drove to the trailheads, hiked, returned to the campsite, had dinner, and went to bed. This routine was my daily pattern. Suddenly, I needed to <em>decide</em> what to do next, and I couldn’t do it effectively. I ended up wasting an entire day watching meaningless videos.</p>
<p>“You do not rise to the level of your goals. You fall to the level of your systems.”</p>
<p>To maintain the mental state I achieved during the trip and act on any of the ideas I had, the first thing I need to do is develop good “systems,” i.e., habits and routines. These need to be simple and maintainable.</p>
<p>My first goal, which is more of a habit, is to <strong>wake up every day at 6 a.m.</strong>, no matter what. If I go to bed late, too bad for me. I will also try to avoid drinking coffee, taking naps during the day, and consuming alcohol. The latter are not difficult as long as I can stick to the first one.</p>
<p>If possible, I’d also like to go for a run, walk, or bike ride as soon as I wake up. When I was hiking, one thing I loved was waking up to the fresh, cold morning air. I suspect it set an uplifting tone for the rest of the day.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>habits</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-23 systems.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2023 15:51:10 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Love the Process</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-01 process vs goal.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>There are two ways of approaching any task and life in general:</p>
<ul>
<li>goal oriented</li>
<li>process oriented</li>
</ul>
<p>For some reason, very likely a mix of cultural and biological, the default is the first approach. You do things in order to get somewhere, to accomplish something.</p>
<p>One of the most important teachings of the various contemplative traditions like Buddhism, Stoicism is that in order to find any semblance of equanimity you need to take the process oriented approach - love the process. The goal is often unattainable and impractical and even when it is attained the attainment itself is momentary and fleeting and once you’re done with it you’re left with a hollowness and a lack of direction.</p>
<p>If you want to run regularly, then you cannot make your running contingent on the next marathon. Every marathon will be over sooner than you’d like. And there will inevitably be long stretches of time in your life when you won’t be able to participate in any running events. If you truly want to become a runner then you should enjoy the process of running for its own sake. You should participate in running events because you’re a runner and not the other way around.</p>
<p>The book “Atomic Habits” has a very good way of putting this - instead of saying that you want to run, you phrase it as you want to become a runner. Instead of saying that you want to read x number of books each year, you say that you want to become an avid reader. This moves the focus from the goal to the process itself.</p>
<p>You can extend this to the broader extent of life. You cannot decide to work hard because you want to accomplish certain goals. Rather you’re able to accomplish your goals in life because you’re a hard working person. The arrow of causality points in the other direction.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>mindfulness</category>
  <category>philosophy</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-01 process vs goal.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2023 17:38:38 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
