<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Journal</title>
<link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.450</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 05:20:45 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Godzilla Minus One</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/movies/2024-01-01 godzilla minus one.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I never imagined that I would like a Kaiju movie. I never understood about their point or their attraction. But Godzilla Minus One was a really good movie. The Godzilla is a metaphor for nuclear holocaust, a force of nature, a tragedy too big to control. Even though it is the central plo point and the story revolves around it, it simply presents the background in which the characters evolve. Godzilla minus one is really the story of a failed Kamikaze pilot who finally finds courage and closure and a way to reconcile with his past. And also a peek into the aftermath of WW2 in Tokyo.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>movie</category>
  <category>japanese</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/movies/2024-01-01 godzilla minus one.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 05:20:45 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Poor Things</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/movies/2024-01-08 poor things.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>After watching the trailer, I was very reluctant to watch Poor Things. But one boring Saturday I had nothing else to do so I watched it in a theater and am I glad I did. What a visual feast! There was not a dull moment in the movie. It felt like I would miss something important if I blinked. Emma Watson and Mark Ruffalo are an absolute delight to watch. Now I need to watch other movies by this genius director.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>movie</category>
  <category>surreal</category>
  <category>fantasy</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/movies/2024-01-08 poor things.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 05:07:56 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Tom Scott</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/series/2023-01-02 tom scott.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Tom Scott stopped making weekly videos today after 10 years. When I first discovered his channel, I binged through all of his videos - at least the ones about travel, and science, and stuff. His departure feels significant. Signaling me to change as well, shed some of my old skin.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/7DKv5H5Frt0?si=rbt9Zs5KVf6QZ49M" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>



 ]]></description>
  <category>youtube</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/series/2023-01-02 tom scott.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2024 05:25:50 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Blue Eye Samurai</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/series/2023-12-26 blue eye samurai.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Netflix has created a masterpiece with Blue Eye Samurai.</p>
<p>There are some standard tropes - lonely samurai, mad skilled, dark past, revenge/mercenary for hire, amateur and naive apprentice, etc. A female protagonist with non-japanese ancestry adds a bit of novelty but not sufficient enough and the first couple of episodes feel pretty standard.</p>
<p>But then as the characters develop and the backstory is revealed, the show really takes off. I distinctly remember watching S1E5 - The Ronin and the Bride - and unable to contain myself with excitement. There is a play in the episode - a story within a story - that is used to reveal Mizo’s past. This is sheer genius. They could have just shown her backstory and the episode would still have been good. But this incorporation of a Japanese myth being told as a play which then parallels Mizu’s life makes this episode great.</p>
<p>Another great thing about this show is that it not emotionless, stoic, cool as many samurai shows tend to be. Sure Mizu is cold-hearted at times but the show has a warmth and gritty authenticity that is very rare. The ending of S1E5, for example, is heart wrenching. If you did not shed a tear or get goosebumps watching this episode, you are a psychopath.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/GNBBpCwAPK4?si=hdXDTk-NvE9eeSwA" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>



 ]]></description>
  <category>series</category>
  <category>anime</category>
  <category>japanese</category>
  <category>netflix</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/series/2023-12-26 blue eye samurai.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 27 Dec 2023 03:44:20 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Happily Ever After</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/podcasts/2023-12-12 happily ever after.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I came across a very interesting idea on a <a href="https://www.hhs.gov/surgeongeneral/priorities/house-calls/dr-laurie-santos-encore/index.html">Happiness Lab adjacent podcast</a></p>
<p>Thanks to Disney fairy tales, or perhaps even before Disney, the phrase “happily ever after” has become commonplace in our society. This phrase seems to suggest that there is a “final state of happiness” which is the goal of life, and once achieved, life remains that way.</p>
<p>This might sound benign, and at best, like a concept for children. However, it’s very possible that the phrase has become ingrained in our collective psyche without us realizing it. Subconsciously, we may find ourselves striving to achieve this elusive goal in life.</p>
<p>The central teaching of Buddhism, which is essentially common sense, states that life is defined by change. No state is permanent, except death. Desiring and pursuing something impermanent is the cause of human suffering.</p>
<p>I find it fascinating that we might have created this illusory goal for ourselves without intending any harm, yet now we are suffering the consequences of this delusion.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>podcast</category>
  <category>happiness-lab</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/podcasts/2023-12-12 happily ever after.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2023 18:41:22 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Severance</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/series/2023-12-12 severance.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I saw <em>Severance</em> a while back when it was released but was reminded of it by a <a href="https://verybadwizards.com/episode/episode-236-your-outie-is-skilled-at-lovemaking-with-paul-bloom">brilliant episode of Very Bad Wizards</a>.</p>
<p>I enjoy reading and watching sci-fi dystopian worlds. It is one of my favorite genres, one that sci-fi explores particularly well. However, rarely do any of these stories get under my skin. Even the deeply poignant ones with no redemptive qualities, like <em>Blade Runner</em>, never perturbed me. I was moved by it emotionally and might have shed a tear at the final scene, but I was feeling things from a distance.</p>
<p>With <em>Severance</em>, though, I felt viscerally disturbed. Even just thinking about it makes me squirm in my chair. It is somewhat reminiscent of <em>1984</em>. I can feel myself being a part of this world. I feel all the frustration and absurdity that the characters experience. I understand their coping mechanisms.</p>
<p>The dark humor of the series makes it more palatable for me than <em>1984</em>. But it is still a hard watch. It is one of my favorite series, and yet I shudder at the thought of watching it again. I know that I will watch the second season when it comes out, but it will be with a mix of awe and anxiety.</p>
<p>Finally, the most disturbing aspects of both <em>Severance</em> and <em>1984</em> are the abject helplessness and the utter lack of hope. You can just feel the unfairness of the world trampling upon everyone, and none of the characters have any chance of escaping. Because <em>Severance</em> is aimed at the ever-optimistic American audience, I just know that in the second season the “small guys” are going to win. But if this series were to stay honest and live up to its true potential, they shouldn’t. This series should follow the same unyielding path as <em>1984</em>. Some stories do need to end in a tragedy.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>series</category>
  <category>podcast</category>
  <category>dystopia</category>
  <category>sci-fi</category>
  <category>very-bad-wizards</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/series/2023-12-12 severance.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2023 14:28:43 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Anatomy of a Fall</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/movies/anatomy-of-a-fall.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Watch for the impressive acting and the gripping story.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/fTrsp5BMloA?si=nvOlJFD4p5efEwLQ" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>



 ]]></description>
  <category>foreign</category>
  <category>thriller</category>
  <category>courtroom</category>
  <category>beautiful</category>
  <category>movie</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/movies/anatomy-of-a-fall.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 25 Nov 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hollow Knight</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/video games/hollow knight.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Hollow Knight is one of the best video games I’ve ever played. I used to play a lot of games during my school and college days but took a break during grad school. I recently resumed playing video games and stumbled upon Hollow Knight by chance.</p>
<p>I began the game unenthusiastically, assuming it would be about a cute little bug navigating Hallownest. I was completely mistaken. This is one of the most brutal and challenging games ever made. The realization hits when you face your first boss. The game shifts from casual to intense in an instant.</p>
<p>What sets this game apart – aside from the gameplay, music, ambiance, themes, lore, story, graphics, essentially everything – is the uncompromising attitude of the designers. The boss fights are insanely challenging, but they are manageable with enough practice. You need to grind, observe, and learn all the boss moves before even thinking of attacking them.</p>
<p>As you delve deeper into the game, the challenge extends beyond the boss fights. The late-game levels, like DeepNest, are tough and require significant effort to clear.</p>
<p>Furthermore, the game lacks manuals or instructions. You learn by doing. Even the maps are initially hidden, encouraging you to explore and learn Hallownest through exploration.</p>
<p>Now that the game is popular, the genius of Team Cherry, its creators, is evident. Their vision and commitment are unparalleled. But I wonder about their thought process during development. They must have received feedback about the difficulty of some bosses or the need for easier navigation, yet they remained true to their convictions. They trusted that players would possess the grit and enthusiasm to keep grinding and learning, a testament to their faith in people and their game’s ability to engage players.</p>
<hr>
<p>Outside gaming, Hollow Knight has impacted my life significantly.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>It has made me more optimistic about humanity. Watching countless speedruns and meme runs on YouTube, I’m constantly aware of my skill level. Seeing the heights people can reach with dedicated practice is humbling and amazing. It shows our great capacity for learning and adapting.</p></li>
<li><p>It has made me realize my love for challenges. Despite the stress and difficulty of clearing hard levels and boss fights, the satisfaction at the end is immense. There are bosses and levels I may never clear, but I enjoy improving with each attempt. It’s a wonderful metaphor for life.</p></li>
<li><p>Surprisingly, it has also influenced my teaching. My courses are challenging, and my exams are generally tough. I used to feel guilty and considered toning it down, but not anymore. I don’t mind the difficulty of my courses or exams, as long as they provide students with ample opportunity to practice, learn, and grow. Some students may excel and do ‘speedruns’, while others might struggle with harder levels – and that’s okay. The joy lies in the process, not the destination.</p></li>
</ol>



 ]]></description>
  <category>challenging</category>
  <category>artsy</category>
  <category>beautiful</category>
  <category>video-game</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/video games/hollow knight.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2023 18:38:51 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>William James - Very Bad Wizards</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/podcasts/2023-11-04 william james podcast.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I’m putting this post here mainly as a bookmark to myself. Sam Harris mentioned this podcast in one of his discussions and so I had a listen.</p>
<p>I don’t remember much about it’s content but I remember thinking just how much William James already knew about psychology and how well he understood the the human mind to make all these claims without doing any scientific research. Of course, he must have read several religious and philosophical texts of his time and infered based on them. But to synthesize something so precise and practical from these abstract and often incorrect sources is nothing short of genius. Having never done any experiments, his claims cannot be called scientific or even emperical, nevertheless as works of fiction and philosophy they contain great ideas that we can investigate today using the scientific method.</p>
<p>My recollection is that in his thesis James concludes that the human society relies entirely on habits and that there is no greater endeavor than to develop good habits. He even lays out some suggestions as to how to go about doing this. I couldn’t agree more.</p>
<p>I will listen to this episode again and take notes.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>habits</category>
  <category>podcast</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/podcasts/2023-11-04 william james podcast.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 04 Nov 2023 18:11:35 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Past Lives</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/movies/2023-10-18 past lives.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>It feels as though the director made this movie just for me. I had to be at this point in my life to truly appreciate it. While my life isn’t as dramatic as the characters’, there is something about the immigrant experience that is so uniquely captured by the film.</p>
<p>Not too far into the movie, you realize that there cannot be any happy ending here. Every ending is going to be sorrowful in its own way - and isn’t that true about life itself? Yet you endure with patience, waiting for your chance to cry at an incomplete catharsis.</p>
<p>This could be one of the finest films I’ve ever watched.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/kA244xewjcI?si=kDj2cn4DmYj6jirT" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>



 ]]></description>
  <category>movies</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/movies/2023-10-18 past lives.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2023 20:21:12 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Smartless - Willem Dafoe</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/podcasts/2023-09-07 smartless willem dafoe.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>On one of my long drives recently, I was listening to the <a href="https://www.smartless.com/episodes/episode/22b8d8d5/willem-dafoe">Smartless episode</a> featuring <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Willem_Dafoe">Willem Dafoe</a>.</p>
<p>He shared a perspective that resonated with me. Although he’s American, he lives in Italy, making him an immigrant there. He mentioned that being an immigrant is a liberating experience for him, allowing him to see things from a distance, with an outsider’s perspective.</p>
<p>I’d never considered it, but it rings true for me as well. Being an immigrant in America, I have the unique vantage point to observe the absurdities, joys, and sorrows of this place, but from a distance. Having lived in another country gives me a completely different perspective, knowing how things could be elsewhere. I can never become too myopic here, as I never get too close to things. There is a sad yet liberating quality to it.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>podcast</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/podcasts/2023-09-07 smartless willem dafoe.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
