<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Journal</title>
<link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.450</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Jun 2024 04:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Candles</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/memories/2024-06-09 candles.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I was driving north on Greenmount and noticed that the traffic lights at many intersections had stopped working. “Typical Baltimore,” was my first thought. Thankfully, it was Sunday morning, and the streets were empty, so it wasn’t too bad. If anything, I was pleasantly surprised to see everyone being civil and patiently waiting for others at the defunct lights. My destination turned out to be devoid of electricity as well. A tree had fallen nearby, taking down some electric wires with it. We sat in darkness, barely shielded from the sweltering heat outside.</p>
<p>It made me think of the power outages we used to have in India when I was a child. Every summer, before the monsoon blessed the land, the rivers would run dry, and so would the supply of electricity. Every Wednesday, or was it Thursday, the coolers would shut themselves off, and we found ourselves sitting in the verandas, fruitlessly fanning ourselves with makeshift handheld fans.</p>
<p>Sometimes the outages were planned, but often they came as a surprise, in the dark of the night. All of us kids would scream at the top of our voices, partly from surprise and partly from joy; we couldn’t possibly do our homework in darkness, could we? It feels surprising now to think of how casually we took it. There were no deadlines to meet, no hurry to get anything done. We’d make impatient calls to MSEB but mostly took life as it came. This was a time to catch up with neighbors we hadn’t chatted with in a while. Did I ever look up at the stars? I don’t remember. I do remember the bats, scary and fascinating, swooping over our heads in the darkness. And the mosquitoes.</p>
<p>A narrow, crooked white candle would emerge from one of the many drawers whose contents were only privy to grandmothers. Light the candle with the cheap matchsticks, tilt it over to let the wax drip, plant the candle on the table. It barely lit a single room, and yet it was enough. It feels a bit sad that I’ll never perform this ritual again. The crooked candles exist no more. I have candles now, but they sit in small mason jars and smell of things other than wax. I light them with a sad kitchen lighter. It’s funny how the things you vividly remember felt so insignificant at the time. I wonder if I’ll remember anything from today a decade from now.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ohJFvjRdKwk?si=A7RUswKZf59LJhkX" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>



 ]]></description>
  <category>memories</category>
  <category>india</category>
  <category>nostalgia</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/memories/2024-06-09 candles.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jun 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Perfect Days</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/movies/2024-02-18 burning.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>This movie has come at an important point in my life. Things have happened in my life that 1) make this movie speak to me on a personal level, and 2) open me up to what it is saying. I’m feeling emotional just thinking about it and trying to write about it.</p>
<p>This movie is a meditation on the joys and sorrows of every day life. Is it not enough to live every day with for itself? Is there any greater goal in life than to be good at your own work? It helps that it is set in Japan which has the culture of acceptance and tranquility.</p>
<p>An important choice the director made was that of reticence. There is very little dialogue in the movie. It says something poignant without words but with</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>japanese</category>
  <category>meditative</category>
  <category>slow</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/movies/2024-02-18 burning.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 24 Feb 2024 18:13:54 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Burning</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/movies/2024-02-24 perfect days.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I’m not sure what I watched. It reminded me a lot of “Memories of a Murder”, one of my favorite movies. But unlike that movie, <em>Burning</em> does not have a firm objective reality. This movie is</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/irBLY-Ev9vo?si=hsdIO9zReAXUEWcl" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>



 ]]></description>
  <category>korean</category>
  <category>thriller</category>
  <category>psychological</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/movies/2024-02-24 perfect days.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 19 Feb 2024 18:13:54 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>American Fiction</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/movies/2024-02-17 american fiction.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 






 ]]></description>
  <category>comedy</category>
  <category>black</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/movies/2024-02-17 american fiction.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2024 14:17:05 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Mind Game</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/movies/2024-02-09 mindgame.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/2fmmCsyK1dY?si=spi_zi6VDhhC6v9Z" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>
<p>Weird as fuck is the only was to describe this movie - at least at the start.</p>
<p>The movie follows a sad, little guy who is stuck in self-pity. Then some random events happen and he gets stuck with 3 other characters on a cast-away type of situation. The rest of the movie is the 4 of them shedding their fake shells and discovering their true selves. I have been thinking about these same things lately and this movie almost feels like it’s written personally for me.</p>
<p>And the story isn’t even the biggest strength of the movie. The visuals, animation style, fractured narrative arcs, unique characters, hilarious chase sequences - all are absolutely top notch.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>movie</category>
  <category>surreal</category>
  <category>anime</category>
  <category>existential</category>
  <category>philosophy</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/movies/2024-02-09 mindgame.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 09 Feb 2024 12:56:13 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Godzilla Minus One</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/movies/2024-01-01 godzilla minus one.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I never imagined that I would like a Kaiju movie. I never understood about their point or their attraction. But Godzilla Minus One was a really good movie. The Godzilla is a metaphor for nuclear holocaust, a force of nature, a tragedy too big to control. Even though it is the central plo point and the story revolves around it, it simply presents the background in which the characters evolve. Godzilla minus one is really the story of a failed Kamikaze pilot who finally finds courage and closure and a way to reconcile with his past. And also a peek into the aftermath of WW2 in Tokyo.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>movie</category>
  <category>japanese</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/movies/2024-01-01 godzilla minus one.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 05:20:45 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Poor Things</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/movies/2024-01-08 poor things.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>After watching the trailer, I was very reluctant to watch Poor Things. But one boring Saturday I had nothing else to do so I watched it in a theater and am I glad I did. What a visual feast! There was not a dull moment in the movie. It felt like I would miss something important if I blinked. Emma Watson and Mark Ruffalo are an absolute delight to watch. Now I need to watch other movies by this genius director.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>movie</category>
  <category>surreal</category>
  <category>fantasy</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/movies/2024-01-08 poor things.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 05:07:56 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Tom Scott</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/series/2023-01-02 tom scott.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Tom Scott stopped making weekly videos today after 10 years. When I first discovered his channel, I binged through all of his videos - at least the ones about travel, and science, and stuff. His departure feels significant. Signaling me to change as well, shed some of my old skin.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/7DKv5H5Frt0?si=rbt9Zs5KVf6QZ49M" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>



 ]]></description>
  <category>youtube</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/series/2023-01-02 tom scott.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2024 05:25:50 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Blue Eye Samurai</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/series/2023-12-26 blue eye samurai.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Netflix has created a masterpiece with Blue Eye Samurai.</p>
<p>There are some standard tropes - lonely samurai, mad skilled, dark past, revenge/mercenary for hire, amateur and naive apprentice, etc. A female protagonist with non-japanese ancestry adds a bit of novelty but not sufficient enough and the first couple of episodes feel pretty standard.</p>
<p>But then as the characters develop and the backstory is revealed, the show really takes off. I distinctly remember watching S1E5 - The Ronin and the Bride - and unable to contain myself with excitement. There is a play in the episode - a story within a story - that is used to reveal Mizo’s past. This is sheer genius. They could have just shown her backstory and the episode would still have been good. But this incorporation of a Japanese myth being told as a play which then parallels Mizu’s life makes this episode great.</p>
<p>Another great thing about this show is that it not emotionless, stoic, cool as many samurai shows tend to be. Sure Mizu is cold-hearted at times but the show has a warmth and gritty authenticity that is very rare. The ending of S1E5, for example, is heart wrenching. If you did not shed a tear or get goosebumps watching this episode, you are a psychopath.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/GNBBpCwAPK4?si=hdXDTk-NvE9eeSwA" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>



 ]]></description>
  <category>series</category>
  <category>anime</category>
  <category>japanese</category>
  <category>netflix</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/series/2023-12-26 blue eye samurai.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 27 Dec 2023 03:44:20 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minimal Setting</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-12-12 minimal setting.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I have a theory about what meditation practice aims to achieve by urging us to “let go”. I believe consciousness or awareness is the bare minimum state of mind required to function. It’s like the OS kernel (or is the BIOS) that loads when your computer starts, before any other program is loaded in working memory. It’s the smallest piece of software necessary to indicate that your mind has booted up.</p>
<p>In our normal existence, we run several other processes on top of it - with thinking being the most energy-consuming one. But we are also engaged in seeing, listening, reading, parsing, talking, etc. There are times when thinking is essential - after all, it’s the foundation of all modern civilization. However, most of the time, we run this program unintentionally. It becomes a runaway program that spawns many threads, each consuming significant resources - like when you have too many tabs open in your web browser.</p>
<p>The goal of meditation is to recognize these redundant threads and shut them down as necessary. It involves realizing that most of the time, you don’t need to load anything other than your OS, and just allow the processor to relax and cool down. Of course, you occasionally need several threads, and then the processor needs to shift into intensive thinking mode, but this shouldn’t be the default state.</p>
<p>This approach is akin to opening a task manager on your computer, deciding which threads are necessary, and terminating the unnecessary ones. I believe this leads to optimized brain function, declutters its RAM, and allows the brain to use its resources for more significant subconscious tasks.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>consciousness</category>
  <category>letting-go</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-12-12 minimal setting.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2023 19:17:29 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Happily Ever After</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/podcasts/2023-12-12 happily ever after.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I came across a very interesting idea on a <a href="https://www.hhs.gov/surgeongeneral/priorities/house-calls/dr-laurie-santos-encore/index.html">Happiness Lab adjacent podcast</a></p>
<p>Thanks to Disney fairy tales, or perhaps even before Disney, the phrase “happily ever after” has become commonplace in our society. This phrase seems to suggest that there is a “final state of happiness” which is the goal of life, and once achieved, life remains that way.</p>
<p>This might sound benign, and at best, like a concept for children. However, it’s very possible that the phrase has become ingrained in our collective psyche without us realizing it. Subconsciously, we may find ourselves striving to achieve this elusive goal in life.</p>
<p>The central teaching of Buddhism, which is essentially common sense, states that life is defined by change. No state is permanent, except death. Desiring and pursuing something impermanent is the cause of human suffering.</p>
<p>I find it fascinating that we might have created this illusory goal for ourselves without intending any harm, yet now we are suffering the consequences of this delusion.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>podcast</category>
  <category>happiness-lab</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/podcasts/2023-12-12 happily ever after.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2023 18:41:22 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Severance</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/series/2023-12-12 severance.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I saw <em>Severance</em> a while back when it was released but was reminded of it by a <a href="https://verybadwizards.com/episode/episode-236-your-outie-is-skilled-at-lovemaking-with-paul-bloom">brilliant episode of Very Bad Wizards</a>.</p>
<p>I enjoy reading and watching sci-fi dystopian worlds. It is one of my favorite genres, one that sci-fi explores particularly well. However, rarely do any of these stories get under my skin. Even the deeply poignant ones with no redemptive qualities, like <em>Blade Runner</em>, never perturbed me. I was moved by it emotionally and might have shed a tear at the final scene, but I was feeling things from a distance.</p>
<p>With <em>Severance</em>, though, I felt viscerally disturbed. Even just thinking about it makes me squirm in my chair. It is somewhat reminiscent of <em>1984</em>. I can feel myself being a part of this world. I feel all the frustration and absurdity that the characters experience. I understand their coping mechanisms.</p>
<p>The dark humor of the series makes it more palatable for me than <em>1984</em>. But it is still a hard watch. It is one of my favorite series, and yet I shudder at the thought of watching it again. I know that I will watch the second season when it comes out, but it will be with a mix of awe and anxiety.</p>
<p>Finally, the most disturbing aspects of both <em>Severance</em> and <em>1984</em> are the abject helplessness and the utter lack of hope. You can just feel the unfairness of the world trampling upon everyone, and none of the characters have any chance of escaping. Because <em>Severance</em> is aimed at the ever-optimistic American audience, I just know that in the second season the “small guys” are going to win. But if this series were to stay honest and live up to its true potential, they shouldn’t. This series should follow the same unyielding path as <em>1984</em>. Some stories do need to end in a tragedy.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>series</category>
  <category>podcast</category>
  <category>dystopia</category>
  <category>sci-fi</category>
  <category>very-bad-wizards</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/series/2023-12-12 severance.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2023 14:28:43 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Setting Intention</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-12-07 setting intention.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>One of the best “hacks” for being mindful and present is to set intentions before starting any task. This includes tasks like planning and concentrated thinking. You just “let your brain know” that this is what it needs to be doing now and it can return to other tasks afterward.</p>
<p>This aligns with the analogy that the brain is a blind automaton with different parts working in parallel. There is communication between the various parts, but this communication is often delayed and imperfect. By setting intentions, you are sending a strong message from one part of the brain to another.</p>
<p>Like right now, there is a lot of chaos happening around me. My internet is down, and I’m supposed to be in a meeting. I have a bunch of deadlines today and I need to get back to planning several things soon. If I just let my mind wander, it will keep jumping from one task to another without actually resolving anything, just increasing my anxiety. Instead, I have decided, as much as possible, that this is my writing time. I do still get thoughts about other things and keep a notebook with me to jot them down to return to them after I’m done. But having this clear intention of writing is essential for me to make it to the end of this sentence with full commitment.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>meditation</category>
  <category>mindfulness</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-12-07 setting intention.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 07 Dec 2023 15:39:27 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Being Present</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-30 present moment.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>“Be Here Now,” the classic book by Ram Dass, is supposed to encapsulate the project of meditation. The more I struggle with meditation, the more I realize how central this principle is to the practice.</p>
<p>My brain is constantly future-looking, sometimes in small ways - I might be brewing coffee and simultaneously thinking about the joy of drinking it afterwards, or I might be biking to work while thinking of what I’m going to do in class today - and sometimes in large ways - I might be doing something mundane like laundry while worrying about my career and long-term future. We are genetically, culturally, and habitually in this constant state of chasing the future.</p>
<p>Why is this bad? Because it represents habituation and a lack of intention. One of the goals of mindfulness is the recognition of conditioning and intentionally choosing to either do something or not. Of course, future planning is a good thing, but it does not need to be done constantly. You need to decide to plan for the future, take care of it, and then let go and return to the present.</p>
<p>It is, of course, easier said than done. I am not sure if it is even possible to be fully present in the current moment. But mindfulness teachings come to the rescue again - the goal is never the reason to do something; the process is. You need to enjoy this process of recognizing that the mind is future-looking and decide if this is where you want it to be. Whether you want it or not, you just make a decision and let go.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>mindfulness</category>
  <category>meditation</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-30 present moment.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 07 Dec 2023 15:00:47 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Saying No</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-27 saying no.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>In a podcast episode on waking up, Oliver Burkeman talks about the necessity to say no to certain things in life because you only have a finite amount of time. This becomes clear when you do the calculation involving the time available and the time required to get things done. This is further emphasized by the fact that we don’t always have the will, energy, or capacity to do the things we would like to do.</p>
<p>Two things worth pointing out:</p>
<ul>
<li>You have to learn to say no to things that you <em>want to do</em>. Just yesterday, I was at a yoga class which was overcrowded. I usually love staying for the final resting pose but I knew that if I stayed until the end, it would take me forever to leave. So, reluctantly, I left early. I still got most of the benefits of the class and managed to leave on time by making a small sacrifice.</li>
<li>There is a difference between conceptually understanding something and experientially understanding it. The effect a concept has on your life is much greater once you’ve internalized it. Even though it’s <em>obvious</em> that you have to say no to things, we don’t always do it. And even when we do, we tend to feel guilty or irritated about it. One has to realize that there is just no alternative. This is a consequence of our finiteness that we need to accept and move on.</li>
</ul>



 ]]></description>
  <category>podcast</category>
  <category>oliver burkeman</category>
  <category>waking up</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-27 saying no.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 27 Nov 2023 12:59:36 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Anatomy of a Fall</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/movies/anatomy-of-a-fall.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Watch for the impressive acting and the gripping story.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/fTrsp5BMloA?si=nvOlJFD4p5efEwLQ" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>



 ]]></description>
  <category>foreign</category>
  <category>thriller</category>
  <category>courtroom</category>
  <category>beautiful</category>
  <category>movie</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/movies/anatomy-of-a-fall.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 25 Nov 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Beginner’s Mind</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-23 beginners mind.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I was listening to a <a href="https://radiolab.org/podcast/interstitium">Radiolab podcast</a> that concluded with a quote by Suzuki Roshi: <em>“In the beginner’s mind there are many possibilities, but in the expert’s there are few.”</em></p>
<p>I’ve never given this much thought, as I’m not particularly drawn to the Zen traditions of koans and contradictions. However, hearing this quote at the end of a science podcast really caught me off-guard and made me see it from a different perspective. I can’t pinpoint exactly what this feeling is, but I feel a tingling sensation hinting at something deeper.</p>
<p>What is it that I’m not seeing? Is it related to my life? My work? Teaching? Meditation?</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>buddhism</category>
  <category>zen</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-23 beginners mind.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2023 19:58:51 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>You Fall to Your Systems</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-23 systems.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>James Clear, the author of “Atomic Habits,” has a quote: “You do not rise to the level of your goals. You fall to the level of your systems.”</p>
<p>I experienced this just today. I completed a five-day hiking trip through the Mojave Desert in Joshua Tree National Park. It was difficult, tiring, exhilarating, and rewarding - everything you’d expect. On the long walks, I brainstormed ways to improve my life, made many plans for the future, and ended up feeling very optimistic.</p>
<p>However, when the trip ended, I just crashed. Surprisingly, I was not mentally or physically exhausted and needed no time to recover. But I had lost my “systems.” During the hikes, I woke up, had breakfast, drove to the trailheads, hiked, returned to the campsite, had dinner, and went to bed. This routine was my daily pattern. Suddenly, I needed to <em>decide</em> what to do next, and I couldn’t do it effectively. I ended up wasting an entire day watching meaningless videos.</p>
<p>“You do not rise to the level of your goals. You fall to the level of your systems.”</p>
<p>To maintain the mental state I achieved during the trip and act on any of the ideas I had, the first thing I need to do is develop good “systems,” i.e., habits and routines. These need to be simple and maintainable.</p>
<p>My first goal, which is more of a habit, is to <strong>wake up every day at 6 a.m.</strong>, no matter what. If I go to bed late, too bad for me. I will also try to avoid drinking coffee, taking naps during the day, and consuming alcohol. The latter are not difficult as long as I can stick to the first one.</p>
<p>If possible, I’d also like to go for a run, walk, or bike ride as soon as I wake up. When I was hiking, one thing I loved was waking up to the fresh, cold morning air. I suspect it set an uplifting tone for the rest of the day.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>habits</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-23 systems.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2023 15:51:10 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hollow Knight</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/video games/hollow knight.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Hollow Knight is one of the best video games I’ve ever played. I used to play a lot of games during my school and college days but took a break during grad school. I recently resumed playing video games and stumbled upon Hollow Knight by chance.</p>
<p>I began the game unenthusiastically, assuming it would be about a cute little bug navigating Hallownest. I was completely mistaken. This is one of the most brutal and challenging games ever made. The realization hits when you face your first boss. The game shifts from casual to intense in an instant.</p>
<p>What sets this game apart – aside from the gameplay, music, ambiance, themes, lore, story, graphics, essentially everything – is the uncompromising attitude of the designers. The boss fights are insanely challenging, but they are manageable with enough practice. You need to grind, observe, and learn all the boss moves before even thinking of attacking them.</p>
<p>As you delve deeper into the game, the challenge extends beyond the boss fights. The late-game levels, like DeepNest, are tough and require significant effort to clear.</p>
<p>Furthermore, the game lacks manuals or instructions. You learn by doing. Even the maps are initially hidden, encouraging you to explore and learn Hallownest through exploration.</p>
<p>Now that the game is popular, the genius of Team Cherry, its creators, is evident. Their vision and commitment are unparalleled. But I wonder about their thought process during development. They must have received feedback about the difficulty of some bosses or the need for easier navigation, yet they remained true to their convictions. They trusted that players would possess the grit and enthusiasm to keep grinding and learning, a testament to their faith in people and their game’s ability to engage players.</p>
<hr>
<p>Outside gaming, Hollow Knight has impacted my life significantly.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>It has made me more optimistic about humanity. Watching countless speedruns and meme runs on YouTube, I’m constantly aware of my skill level. Seeing the heights people can reach with dedicated practice is humbling and amazing. It shows our great capacity for learning and adapting.</p></li>
<li><p>It has made me realize my love for challenges. Despite the stress and difficulty of clearing hard levels and boss fights, the satisfaction at the end is immense. There are bosses and levels I may never clear, but I enjoy improving with each attempt. It’s a wonderful metaphor for life.</p></li>
<li><p>Surprisingly, it has also influenced my teaching. My courses are challenging, and my exams are generally tough. I used to feel guilty and considered toning it down, but not anymore. I don’t mind the difficulty of my courses or exams, as long as they provide students with ample opportunity to practice, learn, and grow. Some students may excel and do ‘speedruns’, while others might struggle with harder levels – and that’s okay. The joy lies in the process, not the destination.</p></li>
</ol>



 ]]></description>
  <category>challenging</category>
  <category>artsy</category>
  <category>beautiful</category>
  <category>video-game</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/video games/hollow knight.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2023 18:38:51 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>William James - Very Bad Wizards</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/podcasts/2023-11-04 william james podcast.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I’m putting this post here mainly as a bookmark to myself. Sam Harris mentioned this podcast in one of his discussions and so I had a listen.</p>
<p>I don’t remember much about it’s content but I remember thinking just how much William James already knew about psychology and how well he understood the the human mind to make all these claims without doing any scientific research. Of course, he must have read several religious and philosophical texts of his time and infered based on them. But to synthesize something so precise and practical from these abstract and often incorrect sources is nothing short of genius. Having never done any experiments, his claims cannot be called scientific or even emperical, nevertheless as works of fiction and philosophy they contain great ideas that we can investigate today using the scientific method.</p>
<p>My recollection is that in his thesis James concludes that the human society relies entirely on habits and that there is no greater endeavor than to develop good habits. He even lays out some suggestions as to how to go about doing this. I couldn’t agree more.</p>
<p>I will listen to this episode again and take notes.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>habits</category>
  <category>podcast</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/podcasts/2023-11-04 william james podcast.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 04 Nov 2023 18:11:35 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
