<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Journal</title>
<link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.450</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Dec 2023 14:41:16 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Multiple Games</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/self/2023-12-14 multiple games.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>My work requires a lot of concentration. I was good at school because I could focus my mind on specific tasks and immerse myself in them. This ability is, of course, a great skill to have today, with human progress relying on our capacity to concentrate like this.</p>
<p>However, life doesn’t operate in the same way. You’re playing multiple games at the same time - work, relationships, health, money, career - and you need to be able to switch back and forth between them as necessary. Each of these games has its own rules and requires different skill sets. Still, being able to focus on one game at a time is essential for success in them.</p>
<p>A meta-skill you need to develop in life is the ability to 1) quickly switch tasks, and 2) once switched, devote yourself wholeheartedly to them. This includes adjusting your emotional state. You might be completely stressed at work, but as soon as you switch to playing the relationships game, you need to load the relevant state into your working memory and stash the work-related state away for later recall.</p>
<p>This is both a good and a bad thing. The bad part is, of course, that you need to acquire this new meta-skill of fast context switching and come up with some organizational principle to manage the data from multiple games. The good parts are more subtle. Often, the negative emotions don’t survive the recall. Unless you’re having a streak of bad luck, you might be doing well in at least one game. Whenever things get too overwhelming in another game, you can switch to this one, even if only momentarily.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>self</category>
  <category>mindfulness</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/self/2023-12-14 multiple games.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 14 Dec 2023 14:41:16 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Life is Hard</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/self/2023-12-13 life is hard.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I was under some stress and anxiety, which, looking back, was completely unnecessary and self-imposed, but did not feel so in the midst of it. Then, suddenly, yesterday, it thawed and gradually went away. I’m trying to figure out what helped me alleviate it.</p>
<p>The simplest reason was perhaps that I had a lot of free time with no deadlines, so I could spend more time contemplating, meditating, and self-observing, thereby appreciating the absurdity of it. This is, of course, the closest we can get to a panacea - the solution to all your problems is to look at yourself inwardly, and given enough time and attention, things would resolve. But I do not always have the luxury to take such long breaks. Perhaps this means that I’m doomed, and when life gets busy, I will get stressed and anxious. All I can do is take small breaks and try to maintain a functional state of anxiety. Which brings me to my second point.</p>
<p>You don’t have to eliminate stress and anxiety. What really sent the ball rolling down the hill for me was a deep realization and acceptance of the fact that life is just hard. There is no reason for it to be otherwise. Sometimes, when something goes in your favor, you start subconsciously hoping for a “happily ever after.” But such a state is purely mythical.</p>
<p>Another realization I had was that, while it is true that things are not all well for me, I just know that sometime, at an unknown time, at an unknown place, things are going to get much worse. I will have some unbearable emotional or physical pain, and if I expect to find equanimity then, I better find equanimity now when things are mostly good with a few wrinkles.</p>
<p>Life is hard, but that’s ok.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>self</category>
  <category>mindfulness</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/self/2023-12-13 life is hard.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Dec 2023 17:24:39 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Life As A Video Game</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/self/2023-12-13 life as a game.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Even though meditation practice is about experience and going beyond words and concepts, the right framing using the right concepts helps to get you there. I was listening to a podcast yesterday on a long drive and wasn’t feeling so great, and the podcast was about the elusive state of Flow. Just as I heard it, I tried to get into a state of flow and immediately my brain turned the road into a video game. I was back inside a <em>Fast and Furious</em> game, but I was neither fast nor furious. Suddenly everything changed. I just imagined the cars in front of me as obstacles I needed to avoid to clear the level. I set my own objectives: the least number of brakes and lane changes. I managed to get myself into a state of flow on I-95!</p>
<p>I hope I am able to replicate this in other scenarios. I have played video games for so long that I would rather live in them than in the real world, and what I’m realizing is that I can trick my brain into forgetting the distinction between the two worlds!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>self</category>
  <category>mindfulness</category>
  <category>framing</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/self/2023-12-13 life as a game.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 13 Dec 2023 13:11:30 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Minimal Setting</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-12-12 minimal setting.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I have a theory about what meditation practice aims to achieve by urging us to “let go”. I believe consciousness or awareness is the bare minimum state of mind required to function. It’s like the OS kernel (or is the BIOS) that loads when your computer starts, before any other program is loaded in working memory. It’s the smallest piece of software necessary to indicate that your mind has booted up.</p>
<p>In our normal existence, we run several other processes on top of it - with thinking being the most energy-consuming one. But we are also engaged in seeing, listening, reading, parsing, talking, etc. There are times when thinking is essential - after all, it’s the foundation of all modern civilization. However, most of the time, we run this program unintentionally. It becomes a runaway program that spawns many threads, each consuming significant resources - like when you have too many tabs open in your web browser.</p>
<p>The goal of meditation is to recognize these redundant threads and shut them down as necessary. It involves realizing that most of the time, you don’t need to load anything other than your OS, and just allow the processor to relax and cool down. Of course, you occasionally need several threads, and then the processor needs to shift into intensive thinking mode, but this shouldn’t be the default state.</p>
<p>This approach is akin to opening a task manager on your computer, deciding which threads are necessary, and terminating the unnecessary ones. I believe this leads to optimized brain function, declutters its RAM, and allows the brain to use its resources for more significant subconscious tasks.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>consciousness</category>
  <category>letting-go</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-12-12 minimal setting.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2023 19:17:29 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>You Know Enough</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/self/2023-12-12 you know enough.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I’ve been feeling a bit irritated, scattered, and frustrated lately. Recent chaos in my life has triggered this state of mind.</p>
<p>I’ve noticed that I keep listening to meditation podcasts and Dharma talks, subconsciously hoping that they’ll help my mind settle down. However, I’m reminded of a point Sam Harris makes in one of his conversations (I’m paraphrasing): there’s only so much conceptual knowledge you need to acquire from others. Sure, you can continue listening to these full-time meditators and gain new insights, but that won’t significantly impact your life. You need to accept that <strong>you know enough</strong>. Now it’s time to buckle down and take extreme ownership.</p>
<p>For me, this means recognizing that my state of frustration and irritation won’t dissipate if I bombard myself with Buddhist wisdom. I need to accept that I am responsible for this state. Although my circumstances triggered it, I am the one sustaining and aggravating it by being myopic and undisciplined.</p>
<p>I know what I need to do. I need to stop searching for more knowledge from others and accept my state for what it is, working on it in ways <strong>I already know</strong>. The promise of meditation is not happiness, but liberation. With a sufficient understanding of self, hopefully, this state will pass sooner rather than later.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>self</category>
  <category>meditation</category>
  <category>practice</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/self/2023-12-12 you know enough.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2023 18:59:56 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Happily Ever After</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/podcasts/2023-12-12 happily ever after.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I came across a very interesting idea on a <a href="https://www.hhs.gov/surgeongeneral/priorities/house-calls/dr-laurie-santos-encore/index.html">Happiness Lab adjacent podcast</a></p>
<p>Thanks to Disney fairy tales, or perhaps even before Disney, the phrase “happily ever after” has become commonplace in our society. This phrase seems to suggest that there is a “final state of happiness” which is the goal of life, and once achieved, life remains that way.</p>
<p>This might sound benign, and at best, like a concept for children. However, it’s very possible that the phrase has become ingrained in our collective psyche without us realizing it. Subconsciously, we may find ourselves striving to achieve this elusive goal in life.</p>
<p>The central teaching of Buddhism, which is essentially common sense, states that life is defined by change. No state is permanent, except death. Desiring and pursuing something impermanent is the cause of human suffering.</p>
<p>I find it fascinating that we might have created this illusory goal for ourselves without intending any harm, yet now we are suffering the consequences of this delusion.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>podcast</category>
  <category>happiness-lab</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/podcasts/2023-12-12 happily ever after.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2023 18:41:22 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Severance</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/series/2023-12-12 severance.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I saw <em>Severance</em> a while back when it was released but was reminded of it by a <a href="https://verybadwizards.com/episode/episode-236-your-outie-is-skilled-at-lovemaking-with-paul-bloom">brilliant episode of Very Bad Wizards</a>.</p>
<p>I enjoy reading and watching sci-fi dystopian worlds. It is one of my favorite genres, one that sci-fi explores particularly well. However, rarely do any of these stories get under my skin. Even the deeply poignant ones with no redemptive qualities, like <em>Blade Runner</em>, never perturbed me. I was moved by it emotionally and might have shed a tear at the final scene, but I was feeling things from a distance.</p>
<p>With <em>Severance</em>, though, I felt viscerally disturbed. Even just thinking about it makes me squirm in my chair. It is somewhat reminiscent of <em>1984</em>. I can feel myself being a part of this world. I feel all the frustration and absurdity that the characters experience. I understand their coping mechanisms.</p>
<p>The dark humor of the series makes it more palatable for me than <em>1984</em>. But it is still a hard watch. It is one of my favorite series, and yet I shudder at the thought of watching it again. I know that I will watch the second season when it comes out, but it will be with a mix of awe and anxiety.</p>
<p>Finally, the most disturbing aspects of both <em>Severance</em> and <em>1984</em> are the abject helplessness and the utter lack of hope. You can just feel the unfairness of the world trampling upon everyone, and none of the characters have any chance of escaping. Because <em>Severance</em> is aimed at the ever-optimistic American audience, I just know that in the second season the “small guys” are going to win. But if this series were to stay honest and live up to its true potential, they shouldn’t. This series should follow the same unyielding path as <em>1984</em>. Some stories do need to end in a tragedy.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>series</category>
  <category>podcast</category>
  <category>dystopia</category>
  <category>sci-fi</category>
  <category>very-bad-wizards</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/series/2023-12-12 severance.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2023 14:28:43 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Setting Intention</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-12-07 setting intention.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>One of the best “hacks” for being mindful and present is to set intentions before starting any task. This includes tasks like planning and concentrated thinking. You just “let your brain know” that this is what it needs to be doing now and it can return to other tasks afterward.</p>
<p>This aligns with the analogy that the brain is a blind automaton with different parts working in parallel. There is communication between the various parts, but this communication is often delayed and imperfect. By setting intentions, you are sending a strong message from one part of the brain to another.</p>
<p>Like right now, there is a lot of chaos happening around me. My internet is down, and I’m supposed to be in a meeting. I have a bunch of deadlines today and I need to get back to planning several things soon. If I just let my mind wander, it will keep jumping from one task to another without actually resolving anything, just increasing my anxiety. Instead, I have decided, as much as possible, that this is my writing time. I do still get thoughts about other things and keep a notebook with me to jot them down to return to them after I’m done. But having this clear intention of writing is essential for me to make it to the end of this sentence with full commitment.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>meditation</category>
  <category>mindfulness</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-12-07 setting intention.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 07 Dec 2023 15:39:27 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Being Present</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-30 present moment.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>“Be Here Now,” the classic book by Ram Dass, is supposed to encapsulate the project of meditation. The more I struggle with meditation, the more I realize how central this principle is to the practice.</p>
<p>My brain is constantly future-looking, sometimes in small ways - I might be brewing coffee and simultaneously thinking about the joy of drinking it afterwards, or I might be biking to work while thinking of what I’m going to do in class today - and sometimes in large ways - I might be doing something mundane like laundry while worrying about my career and long-term future. We are genetically, culturally, and habitually in this constant state of chasing the future.</p>
<p>Why is this bad? Because it represents habituation and a lack of intention. One of the goals of mindfulness is the recognition of conditioning and intentionally choosing to either do something or not. Of course, future planning is a good thing, but it does not need to be done constantly. You need to decide to plan for the future, take care of it, and then let go and return to the present.</p>
<p>It is, of course, easier said than done. I am not sure if it is even possible to be fully present in the current moment. But mindfulness teachings come to the rescue again - the goal is never the reason to do something; the process is. You need to enjoy this process of recognizing that the mind is future-looking and decide if this is where you want it to be. Whether you want it or not, you just make a decision and let go.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>mindfulness</category>
  <category>meditation</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-30 present moment.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 07 Dec 2023 15:00:47 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Pre-Planning</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/self/2023-12-06 preplanning.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>There are two habits I am very serious about developing:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Regulating my sleep – going to bed early and waking up early.</li>
<li>Planning ahead of time.</li>
</ol>
<p>I know people who prepare their entire courses during breaks and then just teach during the semester. They have their lectures, homework, quizzes, and even announcements and emails preprogrammed and just focus on execution during the semester. Pedagogically, I do not favor this approach as I teach better when I improvise during the semester and adapt to my students’ needs.</p>
<p>However, I can no longer sustain improvisation. This semester, I’m teaching just one course on a trivial subject to a small group of students, yet I am overwhelmed by the number of weekly deadlines. Soon, I will be teaching more challenging courses to a larger student body and will have numerous administrative tasks, possibly with additional research duties.</p>
<p>This means preplanning is no longer a luxury, but a <strong>necessity</strong>.</p>
<p>This issue also affected me during my camping trip. I knew months in advance that I would be camping at Joshua Tree National Park. I could have packed and prepared days, if not weeks, in advance. Instead, I packed at the last minute, resulting in a miserable, anxiety-filled, and sleep-deprived trip to the airport.</p>
<p>Now I know the <em>what</em>. I need to figure out the <em>how</em>.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>self</category>
  <category>shortcomings</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/self/2023-12-06 preplanning.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 06 Dec 2023 19:05:50 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Exam Disruptions</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/self/2023-12-06 exam disruption.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>In my most productive days, I consistently track my time using Toggl. I switch the timer as I switch activities, ensuring my entire day is logged. However, this system isn’t completely stable for me and tends to fail when disruptions occur in my life.</p>
<p>Lately, I haven’t been keeping track of my time, and I can pinpoint the last significant disruption to the second exam of my course! I’ve always known that exams are a major stressor for me, but I didn’t realize the impact was so pronounced.</p>
<p>This realization of course does not remove the stressor but now I know what to look out for after the exam.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>self</category>
  <category>life-events</category>
  <category>caution</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/self/2023-12-06 exam disruption.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 06 Dec 2023 18:57:06 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Saying No</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-27 saying no.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>In a podcast episode on waking up, Oliver Burkeman talks about the necessity to say no to certain things in life because you only have a finite amount of time. This becomes clear when you do the calculation involving the time available and the time required to get things done. This is further emphasized by the fact that we don’t always have the will, energy, or capacity to do the things we would like to do.</p>
<p>Two things worth pointing out:</p>
<ul>
<li>You have to learn to say no to things that you <em>want to do</em>. Just yesterday, I was at a yoga class which was overcrowded. I usually love staying for the final resting pose but I knew that if I stayed until the end, it would take me forever to leave. So, reluctantly, I left early. I still got most of the benefits of the class and managed to leave on time by making a small sacrifice.</li>
<li>There is a difference between conceptually understanding something and experientially understanding it. The effect a concept has on your life is much greater once you’ve internalized it. Even though it’s <em>obvious</em> that you have to say no to things, we don’t always do it. And even when we do, we tend to feel guilty or irritated about it. One has to realize that there is just no alternative. This is a consequence of our finiteness that we need to accept and move on.</li>
</ul>



 ]]></description>
  <category>podcast</category>
  <category>oliver burkeman</category>
  <category>waking up</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-27 saying no.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 27 Nov 2023 12:59:36 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Anatomy of a Fall</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/movies/anatomy-of-a-fall.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Watch for the impressive acting and the gripping story.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/fTrsp5BMloA?si=nvOlJFD4p5efEwLQ" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>



 ]]></description>
  <category>foreign</category>
  <category>thriller</category>
  <category>courtroom</category>
  <category>beautiful</category>
  <category>movie</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/movies/anatomy-of-a-fall.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 25 Nov 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Beginner’s Mind</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-23 beginners mind.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I was listening to a <a href="https://radiolab.org/podcast/interstitium">Radiolab podcast</a> that concluded with a quote by Suzuki Roshi: <em>“In the beginner’s mind there are many possibilities, but in the expert’s there are few.”</em></p>
<p>I’ve never given this much thought, as I’m not particularly drawn to the Zen traditions of koans and contradictions. However, hearing this quote at the end of a science podcast really caught me off-guard and made me see it from a different perspective. I can’t pinpoint exactly what this feeling is, but I feel a tingling sensation hinting at something deeper.</p>
<p>What is it that I’m not seeing? Is it related to my life? My work? Teaching? Meditation?</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>buddhism</category>
  <category>zen</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-23 beginners mind.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2023 19:58:51 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>You Fall to Your Systems</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-23 systems.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>James Clear, the author of “Atomic Habits,” has a quote: “You do not rise to the level of your goals. You fall to the level of your systems.”</p>
<p>I experienced this just today. I completed a five-day hiking trip through the Mojave Desert in Joshua Tree National Park. It was difficult, tiring, exhilarating, and rewarding - everything you’d expect. On the long walks, I brainstormed ways to improve my life, made many plans for the future, and ended up feeling very optimistic.</p>
<p>However, when the trip ended, I just crashed. Surprisingly, I was not mentally or physically exhausted and needed no time to recover. But I had lost my “systems.” During the hikes, I woke up, had breakfast, drove to the trailheads, hiked, returned to the campsite, had dinner, and went to bed. This routine was my daily pattern. Suddenly, I needed to <em>decide</em> what to do next, and I couldn’t do it effectively. I ended up wasting an entire day watching meaningless videos.</p>
<p>“You do not rise to the level of your goals. You fall to the level of your systems.”</p>
<p>To maintain the mental state I achieved during the trip and act on any of the ideas I had, the first thing I need to do is develop good “systems,” i.e., habits and routines. These need to be simple and maintainable.</p>
<p>My first goal, which is more of a habit, is to <strong>wake up every day at 6 a.m.</strong>, no matter what. If I go to bed late, too bad for me. I will also try to avoid drinking coffee, taking naps during the day, and consuming alcohol. The latter are not difficult as long as I can stick to the first one.</p>
<p>If possible, I’d also like to go for a run, walk, or bike ride as soon as I wake up. When I was hiking, one thing I loved was waking up to the fresh, cold morning air. I suspect it set an uplifting tone for the rest of the day.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>habits</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-23 systems.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2023 15:51:10 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Hollow Knight</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/video games/hollow knight.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>Hollow Knight is one of the best video games I’ve ever played. I used to play a lot of games during my school and college days but took a break during grad school. I recently resumed playing video games and stumbled upon Hollow Knight by chance.</p>
<p>I began the game unenthusiastically, assuming it would be about a cute little bug navigating Hallownest. I was completely mistaken. This is one of the most brutal and challenging games ever made. The realization hits when you face your first boss. The game shifts from casual to intense in an instant.</p>
<p>What sets this game apart – aside from the gameplay, music, ambiance, themes, lore, story, graphics, essentially everything – is the uncompromising attitude of the designers. The boss fights are insanely challenging, but they are manageable with enough practice. You need to grind, observe, and learn all the boss moves before even thinking of attacking them.</p>
<p>As you delve deeper into the game, the challenge extends beyond the boss fights. The late-game levels, like DeepNest, are tough and require significant effort to clear.</p>
<p>Furthermore, the game lacks manuals or instructions. You learn by doing. Even the maps are initially hidden, encouraging you to explore and learn Hallownest through exploration.</p>
<p>Now that the game is popular, the genius of Team Cherry, its creators, is evident. Their vision and commitment are unparalleled. But I wonder about their thought process during development. They must have received feedback about the difficulty of some bosses or the need for easier navigation, yet they remained true to their convictions. They trusted that players would possess the grit and enthusiasm to keep grinding and learning, a testament to their faith in people and their game’s ability to engage players.</p>
<hr>
<p>Outside gaming, Hollow Knight has impacted my life significantly.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>It has made me more optimistic about humanity. Watching countless speedruns and meme runs on YouTube, I’m constantly aware of my skill level. Seeing the heights people can reach with dedicated practice is humbling and amazing. It shows our great capacity for learning and adapting.</p></li>
<li><p>It has made me realize my love for challenges. Despite the stress and difficulty of clearing hard levels and boss fights, the satisfaction at the end is immense. There are bosses and levels I may never clear, but I enjoy improving with each attempt. It’s a wonderful metaphor for life.</p></li>
<li><p>Surprisingly, it has also influenced my teaching. My courses are challenging, and my exams are generally tough. I used to feel guilty and considered toning it down, but not anymore. I don’t mind the difficulty of my courses or exams, as long as they provide students with ample opportunity to practice, learn, and grow. Some students may excel and do ‘speedruns’, while others might struggle with harder levels – and that’s okay. The joy lies in the process, not the destination.</p></li>
</ol>



 ]]></description>
  <category>challenging</category>
  <category>artsy</category>
  <category>beautiful</category>
  <category>video-game</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/video games/hollow knight.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2023 18:38:51 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>William James - Very Bad Wizards</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/podcasts/2023-11-04 william james podcast.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I’m putting this post here mainly as a bookmark to myself. Sam Harris mentioned this podcast in one of his discussions and so I had a listen.</p>
<p>I don’t remember much about it’s content but I remember thinking just how much William James already knew about psychology and how well he understood the the human mind to make all these claims without doing any scientific research. Of course, he must have read several religious and philosophical texts of his time and infered based on them. But to synthesize something so precise and practical from these abstract and often incorrect sources is nothing short of genius. Having never done any experiments, his claims cannot be called scientific or even emperical, nevertheless as works of fiction and philosophy they contain great ideas that we can investigate today using the scientific method.</p>
<p>My recollection is that in his thesis James concludes that the human society relies entirely on habits and that there is no greater endeavor than to develop good habits. He even lays out some suggestions as to how to go about doing this. I couldn’t agree more.</p>
<p>I will listen to this episode again and take notes.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>habits</category>
  <category>podcast</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/podcasts/2023-11-04 william james podcast.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 04 Nov 2023 18:11:35 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Love the Process</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-01 process vs goal.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>There are two ways of approaching any task and life in general:</p>
<ul>
<li>goal oriented</li>
<li>process oriented</li>
</ul>
<p>For some reason, very likely a mix of cultural and biological, the default is the first approach. You do things in order to get somewhere, to accomplish something.</p>
<p>One of the most important teachings of the various contemplative traditions like Buddhism, Stoicism is that in order to find any semblance of equanimity you need to take the process oriented approach - love the process. The goal is often unattainable and impractical and even when it is attained the attainment itself is momentary and fleeting and once you’re done with it you’re left with a hollowness and a lack of direction.</p>
<p>If you want to run regularly, then you cannot make your running contingent on the next marathon. Every marathon will be over sooner than you’d like. And there will inevitably be long stretches of time in your life when you won’t be able to participate in any running events. If you truly want to become a runner then you should enjoy the process of running for its own sake. You should participate in running events because you’re a runner and not the other way around.</p>
<p>The book “Atomic Habits” has a very good way of putting this - instead of saying that you want to run, you phrase it as you want to become a runner. Instead of saying that you want to read x number of books each year, you say that you want to become an avid reader. This moves the focus from the goal to the process itself.</p>
<p>You can extend this to the broader extent of life. You cannot decide to work hard because you want to accomplish certain goals. Rather you’re able to accomplish your goals in life because you’re a hard working person. The arrow of causality points in the other direction.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>mindfulness</category>
  <category>philosophy</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/philosophy/2023-11-01 process vs goal.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2023 17:38:38 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Casey Neistat</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/uncategorized/2023-10-30 casey neistat.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>I try to stay away from the internet meme culture as much as possible. I no longer find it funny to make fun of people unintentionally (I do still love absurd humor and find many of the controversial comics funny).</p>
<p>I saw a Casey Neistat thumbnail on Nerdwriter1’s channel but I stayed away from it thinking that he’s just another internet meme personality.</p>
<p>But for some reason, I watched one video of Neistat and got hooked. I immediately realized that this wasn’t another internet troll but a master at his craft.</p>
<p>I love that when I open his videos, most of the time I do not know what’s going to happen. And yet, I’m somehow convinced that the video is going to go well! Behind his “bro” facade he is a master storyteller. Rather, his “bro” facade is part of his storytelling act.</p>
<p>I also love his cinematography, editing, music mixing, just everything. Never a boring video.</p>
<p>I’m writing all this because I learned about his work ethic and feel very inspired by it. For quite some time now, I have been struggling with my sleep and work routine. I’m slowly improving but as I’m writing this I’m realizing that I lack role models in this area. The people in my life either don’t do work they like or work hard obsessively for the sake or working hard. But now I have Neistat! He is someone whose work and skill I admire and understand and whose work ethic I hope to emulate.</p>
<p>I hope that this is the kick I needed to pull myself up by the bootstraps. Of course, I feel very motivated and inspired <em>now</em> but the real test is whether this is going to last. Only time will tell.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/C-Cvl3_CH2A?si=RW4KEK-zT6Y3olaE" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>



 ]]></description>
  <category>habits</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/uncategorized/2023-10-30 casey neistat.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2023 00:59:31 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Past Lives</title>
  <link>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/movies/2023-10-18 past lives.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 



<p>It feels as though the director made this movie just for me. I had to be at this point in my life to truly appreciate it. While my life isn’t as dramatic as the characters’, there is something about the immigrant experience that is so uniquely captured by the film.</p>
<p>Not too far into the movie, you realize that there cannot be any happy ending here. Every ending is going to be sorrowful in its own way - and isn’t that true about life itself? Yet you endure with patience, waiting for your chance to cry at an incomplete catharsis.</p>
<p>This could be one of the finest films I’ve ever watched.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/kA244xewjcI?si=kDj2cn4DmYj6jirT" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>



 ]]></description>
  <category>movies</category>
  <guid>https://apurvanakade.github.io/journal/posts/hobbies/movies/2023-10-18 past lives.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2023 20:21:12 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
